A Guide to the Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from Claytor's Book Store 1789-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Miscellaneous Manuscripts Purchased with Books and Magazines from Claytor's Book Store 1789-1938
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1166, etc.
This collection consists of ca. 250 items (2 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from Claytor's Book Store, Charlottesville, Va. in July 1941.
Scope and Content
This is a collection of Americana whose contents and dates vary widely, with most of the materials dating from various time periods throughout the Nineteenth Century. There are numerous documents from Virginia and Pennsylvania, but other states in the eastern U.S. are represented, including Georgia, New York, West Virginia, and New Jersey. There are financial documents, correspondence (letters and postal cards), marriage records, diaries, unpublished poetry and a fragment of a novel, land grants and surveys, and school workbooks. There is material concerning the Fulkerson, Vance, and Stringfellow families, all principally located in Virginia, and Edwin and W.J. Robinson of Pennsylvania (relationship unknown). Specific items include an 1861 Pennsylvania Militia document, a late 1890s visiting list for a home in Washington, D.C., U.S. Navy pay records for the Washington Navy Yard from the 1850s, and paperwork from the 1930s for the Green Bookman bookstore in Charlottesville.
Arrangement
According to a guide prepared in 1972, there was no original filing order of this material. They were initially filed by specific designations and general classification of miscellaneous items. This arrangement has been generally retained, with the papers arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within topic.
Contents List
- Account book from Cartersville, Va. 1793-1796 (Box-folder 1:1)
  Account book from Cartersville, Va. Sales are recorded for crops (corn, tobacco, etc.), alcoholic beverages, clothing, and other items. Dates covered are October 10, 1793-July 11, 1796. #1166
- Daniel Stickley's cyphering book 1827 (Box-folder 1:2)
  An arithmetic workbook containing "vulgar fractions" and word problems. The title page is also signed by Thomas Coles. #1166-a
- Democratic Party miscellanea 1891, n.d. (Box-folder 1:3)
  Newspaper clippings, broadsides, and handwritten speech transcript by an unknown author, concerning Glover Cleveland and the Democratic Party in Pennsylvania and Virginia during the 1890s. #1166-b
- Diaries 1841, 1874 (Box-folder 1:4)
  Two diaries. The first (a fragment) is probably from 1841-1842 (there is an entry for Saturday, Dec. 25th, Christmas Day). Its author is anonymous, and it mentions names such as Wm. H. Blackwell, Alex Brown, Wm. S. Bridgforth, Joe Winn, Joel M. Ragsdale, Josiah B. Wilson, and others. Also mentioned are Petersburg and visitors from Stokes County, N.C. There is much discussion of money lending and owed debts. The second diary is from Minnie Harris of Shady Glen. The diary is written in a Scholar's Guide to Chirography, printed in Portsmouth in 1827. The year of the diary entries is 1874 and the tone of many entries is melancholy. There is much mention of visiting, Bible study, and church attendance. A place name, Middlebrook, is also mentioned, so the author was possibly living in Virginia. #1166-c
- Financial papers 1833-1867 (Box-folder 1:5-6)
  Financial papers include an 1833 paybook kept by Samuel Hattaman for the NS Company, 1840s-1850s wood sales by Henry Walker of Petersburg, Trial Balance for Year Ending 1st March 1848, an 1840s-1850s account book, an 1830s-1850s account book of the Fork Mine and other mining companies, and an 1867 sales book from John F. Rison with Grasty & Rison, Danville, Va. Other names mentioned in the papers are Thomas Anderson (1838) and Henry Walker of Petersburg, Va. (1851). There are numerous papers about Botetourt County, Va. resident George Deisher and his estate from the 1830s-1840s. There is a census or tax report, from ca. 1857, listing names and numbers of white laborers, black laborers, slaves, and hogs. #1166-d
- Fulkerson and Vance families correspondence (Box-folder 1:7)
  Correspondence of the Fulkerson and Vance families in Abingdon, Va., and in Tennessee, Kentucky, Indiana, Missouri, and South Carolina. Primary topics include family and domestic affairs. An October 8, 1814, letter from James Vance to his mother comments on his readiness to fight in the War of 1812. An October 30, 1851, letter from Jim Fulkerson to his sister Kate mentions "an exciting election here between the secessionist and the cooperationist, [the latter] carried the day by a long majority." He mentions "They are all disunionist but the party that carried the day were for waiting untill the other states help them to break up the Union." There is a January 20, 1862, letter from Margaret Fulkerson to "My dear Son," in which she writes that "it gave us considerable relief to know that you were once more in Camp." She often thinks "how little the bad weather affects us in comparison with those in the Army." There is much discussion of family and home events. #1166-e
- Green Bookman (bookstore) papers 1936-1938, n.d. (Box-folder 1:8)
  Correspondence, an invoice, and merchandise lists from the Green Bookman, a bookstore located in Bridgewater and later Charlottesville, Va., and its proprietor, Charles L. Worthington. There is a correspondence about a possible book purchase between Worthington and George B. Zehmer, University of Virginia Extension Division director. #1166-f
- Land grants and survey from North Carolina, Pennsylvania, and South Carolina 1789-1799 (Box-folder 1:9, oversize)
  A 1789 Bladen County, N.C., land grant; a 1797 Franklin County, Pa., land grant from Thomas Durboraus to James Meeks; and a 1799 Prince George's Parish, S.C., land survey for Caleb Sutton and Thomas Hoddy. #1166-g
- Legal documents from Virginia and Georgia 1851-1929 (Box-folder 1:10)
  A March 1, 1851, deposition of Asa Brown in Loudon County, Va., attesting to the War of 1812 service of Robert Bogue in the company commanded by Captain Stephen Daniel in the 5th Regiment of Virginia Militia commanded by Colonel Street and later in the 5th Regiment of Regulars commanded by Colonel Peter Little. Also included is a July 2, 1866, notice of debt in Leesburg, Va., for William and John Grimes to the Commonwealth of Virginia. There is a mostly illegible 1873 legal document from Bibb County, Ga. Also included is "An ordinance to further prohibit ...ardent spirits" in Petersburg, Va., dated March 19, 1918, with a handwritten note indicating "Passed Sept. 20, 1921." There is a January 1926 legal document concerning an adultery charge involving Mary Lillian Licklider and Harry G. Tonkin. Also included is a document addressed to the Judicial Council in Virginia elaborating upon an April 30, 1929, report on handling court records. #1166-h
- Letters from various correspondents 1844-1932 (Box-folder 1:11)
  Miscellaneouse letters. Many are without dates and the names of correspondents on some are illegible or hard to read. Names and places mentioned include: "Mrs. Frank W. Edmonson, Oak Point;" "Dear Mrs. Faulkner" [from] Lila R.; and "My Dear Mr. Ritchie." Other names, locations, and dates include: Henry Buckler, Harrisburg, Pa., from a correspondent in Pittsburgh (October 14, 1844); Mr. W.G. Catlett from a New Orleans correspondent (November 10, 1866); to Aunt Mat and Kate from Mary (Mrs. Thomas Totterdale), Clarksburg, W.Va. (December 1, 1908); to Mr. J.A. Patterson of Charlottesville, Va., from the Jones Brothers Company, Boston, Mass. (November 5, 1930); to John Armstrong Chanler from W.G. Maxwell, New York (April 13, 1931); and to Mrs. Findley Braden from the Presbyterian Publishing Company (June 22, 1932). #1166-i
- Manuscript of unidentified Southern novel ca. 1850 (Box-folder 2:1-2)
  Pages 200-620 of a handwritten manuscript novel. Two of the characters are named Eustace Mortimer and Garnet. Some of the story concerns an insurgency to "incite a servile insurrection" in the South and the measures taken to counter it (see page 372). The manuscript is divided into 2 parts, each bound on the left margin with string. #1166-j
- Marriage licenses and records and wedding invitation from Virginia and New York. 1838-1914 (Box-folder 2:3)
  Marriage licenses of Abraham Alger and Rebecca Stover (February 26, 1838, Shendandoah County, Va.) and John Wade, Jr., and Adelia Ann Ashingherst (December 3, 1863, Franklin County, Va.). Record of marriages in East Hamburgh, Erie County, N.Y. (1891-1893). Invitation with envelope sent to Mr. and Mrs. E.R. McKethan for the wedding of Alfred Moore Scales and Mary Leigh Pell (daughter of Reverend Edward Leigh Pell) (September 16, 1914, Richmond, Va.). #1166-k
- Miscellaneous items 1865-1919, n.d. (Box-folder 2:4)
  Undated items include: a needlwork bookmark; a calling card with Miss Kate Chambers written on it; handwritten notes (and examinations--"Preliminary Examination") on physiology; geography, and history; potpourri preparation directions; a note about Presbyters and the Directory of Worship revision; an undated list of names; and a mostly illegible speech transcript ("With the permission of our President, leaders, members of the senate, I have prepared..."). An 1865-1866 copy book with "Josephine Strickland" written in it. An 1878 list of merchandise. Three 1882 postal cards to Henry Lowry, Bedford, Va. 1887 Ladies Note- Book and Calendar. A 1908 postal card to Samuel Shreckshire, Raphine, Va. January 1911 newspaper clippings which appeared in the Evening bulletin. ("The story of Long Beach, New Jersey"). Robert D. Coxe contributed to reminiscences about the New Jersey shore area. A February 10, 1911, poultry farming scholarship certificate from the International Correspondence School, Scranton, Pa., for R.N. Watts of Memphis, Tenn. An April 14, 1913, telegram to Richard Oulahan about McAdoo. A July 1919 certificate from the Virginia Board of Education for Margaret Lassiter to teach in public elementary schools. #1166-l
- An act providing for the immediate expenses of the Volunteer Militia of this State now in Actual Service 1861 May 10 (Box-folder 2:5)
  A handwritten legislative document authorized by the Pennsylvania General Assembly to supply the necessary contingent expenses of Pennsylvania militia in the service of the United States. The names (but not signatures) of the Speaker of the Pennsylvania House of Representative, the Speaker of the Pennsylvania Senate, and the Governor of Pennsylvania are at the end of the document (Elisha W. Davis, L.W. Hall, and A.G Curtin). #1166-m
- Poems n.d. (Box-folder 2:6)
  Two undated, anonymous poems: Tired and The wanderer's return. Also included is Memories of the scarlet and blue by Frank G. Dawson. #1166-n
- Edwin P. and W.J. Robinson papers 1858-1904 (Box-folder 2:7)
  Letters, receipts, telegrams, envelopes, and a cancelled check indentified to Edwin P. and W.J. Robinson. Their relationship, if any, is not known. Locations named on the documents include places in New York, Missouri, Illinois, and Pennsylvania, with the latter most prevalent. (Dauphin, Pa., is mentioned on a number of documents.) Edwin Robinson's name includes the title "Rev." on several documents. He may have been Presbyterian. #1166-o
- Stringfellow family papers 1833-1860, n.d. (Box-folder 2:8)
  Letters, legal documents (wills, indentures, estate papers, etc.), deeds, financial documents, invitations, and other papers from Stringfellow family members living principally in Culpeper County, Va. Most of the papers were are related to James L. Stringfellow, but there is also mention of Thornton and Lawrence Stringfellow. Various papers concerning George Deisher (of Botetourt County, Va.) and his estate are included in the materials but the relationship of any member of the Stringfellow family to Deisher is unclear. Many of the documents concern estate law and there are numerous legal documents prepared in Fauquier County, Va. #1166-p
- Study notebook of Alexander R. Pendleton 1866-1869 (Box-folder 2:9)
  Bound notebook belonging to Alexander R. Pendleton, Martinsburg, Va. while a student at the College of New Jersey (Princeton University). Topics include elocution and geology. Professor Guyot is mentioned as a geology instructor and there is also mention of Nassau Hall. #1166-q
- Surveying book of F.D. Eastham 1858-1896 (Box-folder 2:10)
  Surveying book kept by F.D. Eastham, covers the stating and working out of problems in geometry and trigonometry as the two relate to land surveying. There is an entry dated March 16th, 1896, entitled "Scholars present March 16th, 1896." #1166-r
- United States Navy documents 1854-1856 (Box-folder 2:11)
  Pay receipts for officers signed at the Washington Navy Yard by Thomas B. Nalle, purser in the United States Navy. Also included is a 2-page handwritten copy of Navy regulations. #1166-s
- Visiting list for 1710 16th Street 1898-1899 (Box-folder 2:12)
  Bound notebook embossed on the cover with "Visiting List." Names and addresses of visitors in 1898-1899 to 1710 16th Street, Washington, D.C., are handwritten in the notebook, alphabetically by visitors' surnames. There is no information on the owner of the home for which the book was kept. #1166-t
- West Virginia documents 1898-1904 (Box-folder 2:13)
  Fayette County tax receipts from 1904 for the Low Moor Iron Company, made out to Sheriff N. Daniel, and an 1898 lawsuit concerning the location of the county seat of Randolph County, W.Va. #1166-u